<TABLE_DEFINITIONS Table="CAEMP25N" Name="Total Full-Time and Part-Time Employment by NAICS Industry" Source="USDOC/BEA/RD"><LINE><Code>10</Code><Description>Total employment (number of jobs)</Description><Definition>A count of jobs, both full-time and part-time. It includes wage and salary jobs, sole proprietorships, and individual general partners, but not unpaid family workers nor volunteers.</Definition></LINE><LINE><Code>20</Code><Description>Wage and salary employment</Description><Definition>Wage and salary employment, also referred to as wage and salary jobs, measures the average annual number of full-time and part-time jobs in each area by place of work. All jobs for which wages and salaries are paid are counted. Although compensation paid to jurors, expert legal witnesses, prisoners, and justices of the peace (for marriage fees), is counted in wages and salaries, these activities are not counted as jobs in wage and salary employment. Corporate directorships are counted as self-employment. The following description of the sources and methods used in estimating wage and salary employment is divided into two sections: Employment in industries covered by unemployment insurance (UI) programs, and employment in industries not covered by UI.</Definition></LINE><LINE><Code>40</Code><Description>Proprietors employment</Description><Definition>Consists of farm proprietors employment and nonfarm proprietors employment.</Definition></LINE><LINE><Code>50</Code><Description>Farm proprietors employment</Description><Definition>Consists of sole proprietors and non-corporate partners in the farm industry.</Definition></LINE><LINE><Code>60</Code><Description>Nonfarm proprietors employment</Description><Definition>Consists of the number of nonfarm sole proprietorships and the number of individual general partners in nonfarm partnerships.</Definition></LINE><LINE><Code>70</Code><Description>Farm employment</Description><Definition>Farm employment is the number of workers engaged in the direct production of agricultural commodities, either livestock or crops; whether as a sole proprietor, partner, or hired laborer.</Definition></LINE><LINE><Code>80</Code><Description>Nonfarm employment</Description><Definition>Nonfarm employment consists of nonfarm wage and salary employment and nonfarm proprietors employment. Nonfarm proprietors employment consist of the number of sole proprietorships and the number of individual general partners in partnerships. The nonfarm proprietors employment estimates resemble the wage and salary employment estimates in that both series measure jobs-as opposed to workers-on a full-time and part-time basis. However, because of limitations in source data, two important measurement differences exist between the two sets of estimates. First, the nonfarm proprietors employment estimates are largely on a place-of-residence basis rather than on the preferred place-of-work basis. Second, the nonfarm proprietors employment estimates reflect the total number of sole proprietorships or individual general partners active at any time during the year-as opposed to the annual average measure used for wage and salary employment.</Definition></LINE><LINE><Code>90</Code><Description>Private nonfarm employment</Description><Definition>Private nonfarm employment is the sum of wage and salary employment and nonfarm proprietors employment, excluding farm and government.</Definition></LINE><LINE><Code>100</Code><Description>Forestry, fishing, and related activities</Description><Definition>The Forestry, fishing, related activities NAICS sector comprises establishments primarily engaged in harvesting timber, and harvesting fish and other animals from a farm, ranch, or their natural habitats.The sector distinguishes one basic activity: agricultural support. Agricultural support activities include establishments that perform one or more activities associated with farm operation, such as soil preparation, planting, harvesting, and management, on a contract or fee basis.Excluded from the Forestry, Hunting and Fishing sector are establishments primarily engaged in agricultural research and establishments primarily engaged in administering programs for regulating and conserving land, mineral, wildlife, and forest use. These establishments are classified in Industry 54171, Research and Development in the Physical, Engineering, and Life Sciences; and Industry 92412, Administration of Conservation Programs, respectively.Industries in the Fishing, Hunting, and Trapping subsector harvest fish and other wild animals from their natural habitats and are dependent upon a continued supply of the natural resource. The harvesting of fish is the predominant economic activity of this subsector and it usually requires specialized vessels that, by the nature of their size, configuration and equipment, are not suitable for any other type of production, such as transportation.Hunting and trapping activities utilize a wide variety of production processes and are classified in the same subsector as fishing because the availability of resources and the constraints imposed, such as conservation requirements and proper habitat maintenance, are similar.Industries in the Forestry and Logging subsector grow and harvest timber on a long production cycle (i.e., of 10 years or more). Long production cycles use different production processes than short production cycles, which require more horticultural interventions prior to harvest, resulting in processes more similar to those found in the Crop Production subsector. Consequently, Christmas tree production and other production involving production cycles of less than 10 years, are classified in the Crop Production subsector.Industries in this subsector specialize in different stages of the production cycle. Reforestation requires production of seedlings in specialized nurseries. Timber production requires natural forest or suitable areas of land that are available for a long duration. The maturation time for timber depends upon the species of tree, the climatic conditions of the region, and the intended purpose of the timber. The harvesting of timber (except when done on an extremely small scale) requires specialized machinery unique to the industry. Establishments gathering forest products, such as gums, barks, balsam needles, rhizomes, fibers, Spanish moss, and ginseng and truffles, are also included in this subsector.Industries in the Support Activities for Agriculture and Forestry subsector provide support services that are an essential part of agricultural and forestry production. These support activities may be performed by the agriculture or forestry producing establishment or conducted independently as an alternative source of inputs required for the production process for a given crop, animal, or forestry industry. Establishments that primarily perform these activities independent of the agriculture or forestry producing establishment are in this subsector.</Definition></LINE><LINE><Code>200</Code><Description>Mining, quarrying, and oil and gas extraction</Description><Definition>This sector under NAICS comprises establishments that extract naturally occurring mineral solids, such as coal and ores; liquid minerals, such as crude petroleum; and gases, such as natural gas. The term mining is used in the broad sense to include quarrying, well operations, beneficiating (e.g., crushing, screening, washing, and flotation), and other preparation customarily performed at the mine site, or as a part of mining activity. The Mining sector distinguishes two basic activities: mine operation and mining support activities. Mine operation includes establishments operating mines, quarries, or oil and gas wells on their own account or for others on a contract or fee basis. Mining support activities include establishments that perform exploration (except geophysical surveying) and/or other mining services on a contract or fee basis (except mine site preparation and construction of oil/gas pipelines).</Definition></LINE><LINE><Code>300</Code><Description>Utilities</Description><Definition>The Utilities NAICS sector comprises establishments engaged in the provision of the following utility services: electric power, natural gas, steam supply, water supply, and sewage removal. Within this sector, the specific activities associated with the utility services provided vary by utility: electric power includes generation, transmission, and distribution; natural gas includes distribution; steam supply includes provision and/or distribution; water supply includes treatment and distribution; and sewage removal includes collection, treatment, and disposal of waste through sewer systems and sewage treatment facilities.</Definition></LINE><LINE><Code>400</Code><Description>Construction</Description><Definition>The term "Construction" is used in both the SIC system and in NAICS, but it does not have the same definition in both systems. SIC definition:This SIC division includes establishments primarily engaged in construction. The term construction includes new work, additions, alterations, reconstruction, installations, and repairs. Construction activities are generally administered or managed from a relatively fixed place of business, but the actual construction work is performed at one or more different sites. If a company has more than one relatively fixed place of business from which it undertakes or manages construction activities and for which separate data on the number of employees, payroll, receipts, and other establishment-type records are maintained, each such place of business is considered a separate construction establishment. Three broad types of construction activity are covered: (1) building construction by general contractors or by operative builders; (2) heavy construction other than building by general contractors and special trade contractors; and (3) construction activity by other special trade contractors. NAICS definition:The Construction (NAICS) sector comprises establishments primarily engaged in the construction of buildings or engineering projects (e.g., highways an utility systems). Establishments primarily engaged in the preparation of sites for new construction and establishments primarily engaged in subdividing land for sale as building sites also are included in this sector. Construction work done may include new work, additions, alterations, or maintenance and repairs. Activities of these establishments generally are managed at a fixed place of business, but they usually perform construction activities at multiple project sites. Production responsibilities in this sector are usually specified in (1) contracts with the owners of construction projects (prime contracts) or (2) contracts with other construction establishments (subcontracts).</Definition></LINE><LINE><Code>500</Code><Description>Manufacturing</Description><Definition>The term "Manufacturing" is used in both the SIC system and in NAICS, but it does not have the same definition in both systems. SIC definition:The manufacturing SIC division includes establishments engaged in the mechanical or chemical transformation of materials or substances into new products. These establishments are usually described as plants, factories, or mills and characteristically use power driven machines and materials handling equipment. Establishments engaged in assembling component parts of manufactured products are also considered manufacturing if the new product is neither a structure nor other fixed improvement. Also included is the blending of materials, such as lubricating oils, plastics resins, or liquors. NAICS definition:The Manufacturing NAICS sector comprises establishments engaged in the mechanical, physical, or chemical transformation of materials, substances, or components into new products. The assembling of component parts of manufactured products is considered manufacturing, except in cases where the activity is appropriately classified in Sector 23, Construction. Establishments in the Manufacturing sector are often described as plants, factories, or mills and characteristically use power-driven machines and materials-handling equipment. However, establishments that transform materials or substances into new products by hand or in the worker's home and those engaged in selling to the general public products made on the same premises from which they are sold, such as bakeries, candy stores, and custom tailors, may also be included in this sector. Manufacturing establishments may process materials or may contract with other establishments to process their materials for them. Both types of establishments are included in manufacturing.</Definition></LINE><LINE><Code>600</Code><Description>Wholesale trade</Description><Definition>The term "wholesale trade" is used in the SIC system and in NAICS, but it does not have the same definition in both systems. SIC definition:This SIC division includes establishments or places of business primarily engaged in selling merchandise to retailers; to industrial, commercial, institutional, farm, construction contractors, or professional business users; or to other wholesalers; or acting as agents or brokers in buying merchandise for or selling merchandise to such persons or companies. NAICS definition:The Wholesale Trade NAICS sector comprises establishments engaged in wholesaling merchandise, generally without transformation, and rendering services incidental to the sale of merchandise. The merchandise described in this sector includes the outputs of agriculture, mining, manufacturing, and certain information industries, such as publishing.</Definition></LINE><LINE><Code>700</Code><Description>Retail trade</Description><Definition>The term "retail trade" is used in the SIC system and in NAICS, but it does not have the same definition in both systems. SIC definition:This SIC division includes establishments engaged in selling merchandise for personal or household consumption and rendering services incidental to the sale of the goods. In general, retail establishments are classified by kind of business according to the principal lines of commodities sold (groceries, hardware, etc.), or the usual trade designation (drug store, cigar store, etc.). Some of the important characteristics of retail trade establishments are: the establishment is usually a place of business and is engaged in activities to attract the general public to buy; the establishment buys or receives merchandise as well as sells; the establishment may process its products, but such processing is incidental or subordinate to selling; the establishment is considered as retail in the trade; and the establishment sells to customers for personal or household use. Not all of these characteristics need be present and some are modified by trade practice. NAICS definition:The Retail Trade NAICS sector comprises establishments engaged in retailing merchandise, generally without transformation, and rendering services incidental to the sale of merchandise. The retailing process is the final step in the distribution of merchandise; retailers are, therefore, organized to sell merchandise in small quantities to the general public. This sector comprises two main types of retailers: store and nonstore retailers. 1. Store retailers operate fixed point-of-sale locations, located and designed to attract a high volume of walk-in customers. In general, retail stores have extensive displays of merchandise and use mass-media advertising to attract customers. They typically sell merchandise to the general public for personal or household consumption, but some also serve business and institutional clients. These include establishments, such as office supply stores, computer and software stores, building materials dealers, plumbing supply stores, and electrical supply stores. Catalog showrooms, gasoline stations, automotive dealers, and mobile home dealers are treated as store retailers. In addition to retailing merchandise, some types of store retailers are also engaged in the provision of after-sales services, such as repair and installation. For example, new automobile dealers, electronic and appliance stores, and musical instrument and supply stores often provide repair services. As a general rule, establishments engaged in retailing merchandise and providing after-sales services are classified in this sector. 2. Nonstore retailers, like store retailers, are organized to serve the general public, but their retailing methods differ. The establishments of this subsector reach customers and market merchandise with methods, such as the broadcasting of "infomercials," the broadcasting and publishing of direct-response advertising, the publishing of paper and electronic catalogs, door-to-door solicitation, in-home demonstration, selling from portable stalls (street vendors, except food), and distribution through vending machines. Establishments engaged in the direct sale (nonstore) of products, such as home heating oil dealers and home delivery newspaper routes are included here.</Definition></LINE><LINE><Code>800</Code><Description>Transportation and warehousing</Description><Definition>The Transportation and Warehousing NAICS sector includes industries providing transportation of passengers and cargo, warehousing and storage for goods, scenic and sightseeing transportation, and support activities related to modes of transportation. Establishments in these industries use transportation equipment or transportation related facilities as a productive asset. The type of equipment depends on the mode of transportation. The modes of transportation are air, rail, water, road, and pipeline.</Definition></LINE><LINE><Code>900</Code><Description>Information</Description><Definition>The Information NAICS sector comprises establishments engaged in the following processes: (a) producing and distributing information and cultural products, (b) providing the means to transmit or distribute these products as well as data or communications, and (c) processing data.  The main components of this sector are the publishing industries, including software publishing, and both traditional publishing and publishing exclusively on the Internet; the motion picture and sound recording industries; the broadcasting industries, including traditional broadcasting and those broadcasting exclusively over the Internet; the telecommunications industries; the industries known as Internet service providers and Web search portals; data processing industries; and the information services industries.</Definition></LINE><LINE><Code>1000</Code><Description>Finance and insurance</Description><Definition>The Finance and Insurance NAICS sector comprises establishments primarily engaged in financial transactions (transactions involving the creation, liquidation, or change in ownership of financial assets) and/or in facilitating financial transactions. Three principal types of activities are identified:  Raising funds by taking deposits and/or issuing securities and, in the process, incurring liabilities. Establishments engaged in this activity use raised funds to acquire financial assets by making loans and/or purchasing securities. Putting themselves at risk, they channel funds from lenders to borrowers and transform or repackage the funds with respect to maturity, scale and risk. This activity is known as financial intermediation.  Pooling of risk by underwriting insurance and annuities. Establishments engaged in this activity collect fees, insurance premiums, or annuity considerations; build up reserves; invest those reserves; and make contractual payments. Fees are based on the expected incidence of the insured risk and the expected return on investment.  Providing specialized services facilitating or supporting financial intermediation, insurance, and employee benefit programs.  In addition, monetary authorities charged with monetary control are included in this sector.</Definition></LINE><LINE><Code>1100</Code><Description>Real estate and rental and leasing</Description><Definition>The Real Estate and Rental and Leasing NAICS sector comprises establishments primarily engaged in renting, leasing, or otherwise allowing the use of tangible or intangible assets, and establishments providing related services. The major portion of this sector comprises establishments that rent, lease, or otherwise allow the use of their own assets by others. The assets may be tangible, as is the case of real estate and equipment, or intangible, as is the case with patents and trademarks. This sector also includes establishments primarily engaged in managing real estate for others, selling, renting and/or buying real estate for others, and appraising real estate. These activities are closely related to this sector's main activity, and it was felt that from a production basis they would best be included here. In addition, a substantial proportion of property management is self-performed by lessors. The main components of this sector are the real estate lessors industries (including equity real estate investment trusts (REITs)); equipment lessors industries (including motor vehicles, computers, and consumer goods); and lessors of nonfinancial intangible assets (except copyrighted works).</Definition></LINE><LINE><Code>1200</Code><Description>Professional, scientific, and technical services</Description><Definition>The Professional, Scientific, and Technical Services NAICS sector comprises establishments that specialize in performing professional, scientific, and technical activities for others. These activities require a high degree of expertise and training. The establishments in this sector specialize according to expertise and provide these services to clients in a variety of industries and, in some cases, to households. Activities performed include: legal advice and representation; accounting, bookkeeping, and payroll services; architectural, engineering, and specialized design services; computer services; consulting services; research services; advertising services; photographic services; translation and interpretation services; veterinary services; and other professional, scientific, and technical services.This sector excludes establishments primarily engaged in providing a range of day-to-day office administrative services, such as financial planning, billing and recordkeeping, personnel, and physical distribution and logistics. These establishments are classified in Sector 56, Administrative and Support and Waste Management and Remediation Services.</Definition></LINE><LINE><Code>1300</Code><Description>Management of companies and enterprises</Description><Definition>The Management of Companies and Enterprises NAICS sector comprises (1) establishments that hold the securities of (or other equity interests in) companies and enterprises for the purpose of owning a controlling interest or influencing management decisions or (2) establishments (except government establishments) that administer, oversee, and manage establishments of the company or enterprise and that normally undertake the strategic or organizational planning and decision-making role of the company or enterprise. Establishments that administer, oversee, and manage may hold the securities of the company or enterprise.  Establishments in this sector perform essential activities that are often undertaken, in-house, by establishments in many sectors of the economy. By consolidating the performance of these activities of the enterprise at one establishment, economies of scale are achieved.</Definition></LINE><LINE><Code>1400</Code><Description>Administrative and support and waste management and remediation services</Description><Definition>The Administrative and Support and Waste Management and Remediation Services NAICS sector comprises establishments performing routine support activities for the day-to-day operations of other organizations. These essential activities are often undertaken in-house by establishments in many sectors of the economy. The establishments in this sector specialize in one or more of these support activities and provide these services to clients in a variety of industries and, in some cases, to households. Activities performed include: office administration, hiring and placing of personnel, document preparation and similar clerical services, solicitation, collection, security and surveillance services, cleaning, and waste disposal services.  The administrative and management activities performed by establishments in this sector are typically on a contract or fee basis. These activities may also be performed by establishments that are part of the company or enterprise. However, establishments involved in administering, overseeing, and managing other establishments of the company or enterprise, are classified in Sector 55, Management of Companies and Enterprises. These establishments normally undertake the strategic and organizational planning and decision-making role of the company or enterprise. Government establishments engaged in administering, overseeing, and managing governmental programs are classified in Sector 92, Public Administration.</Definition></LINE><LINE><Code>1500</Code><Description>Educational services</Description><Definition>The term "Educational Services" is used in both the SIC system and in NAICS, but it does not have the same definition in both systems.SIC definition: This SIC major group (82) includes establishments providing academic or technical instruction. Also included are establishments providing educational services such as libraries, student exchange programs, and curriculum development. Schools for the instruction of beauticians and cosmetologists are classified in Industry 7231, and barber colleges are classified in Industry 7241. Establishments primarily engaged in providing job training for the unemployed, the underemployed, the handicapped, and to persons who have a job market disadvantage because of lack of education, job skill or experience are classified in Industry 8331.NAICS definition:The Educational Services (NAICS) sector comprises establishments that provide instruction and training in a wide variety of subjects. This instruction and training is provided by specialized establishments, such as schools, colleges, universities, and training centers. These establishments may be privately owned and operated for profit or not for profit, or they may be publicly owned and operated. They may also offer food and accommodation services to their students. For the public sector, the income and employment are classified by level of government- federal, state, and local. The estimates for the federal government are sub classified into civilian and military. The different treatment of the private and public sectors means that BEA's state and local government industry includes public education, public hospitals, and other types of government services while BEA reports only private schools in its educational services industry corresponding to NAICS code 61 and only private hospitals in its hospitals industry corresponding to NAICS code 622.  Educational services (NAICS) are usually delivered by teachers or instructors that explain, tell, demonstrate, supervise, and direct learning. Instruction is imparted in diverse settings, such as educational institutions, the workplace, or the home through correspondence, television, or other means. It can be adapted to the particular needs of the students, for example sign language can replace verbal language for teaching students with hearing impairments. All industries in the sector share this commonality of process, namely, labor inputs of instructors with the requisite subject matter expertise and teaching ability.</Definition></LINE><LINE><Code>1600</Code><Description>Health care and social assistance</Description><Definition>The Health Care and Social Assistance NAICS sector comprises establishments providing health care and social assistance for individuals. The sector includes both health care and social assistance because it is sometimes difficult to distinguish between the boundaries of these two activities. The industries in this sector are arranged on a continuum starting with those establishments providing medical care exclusively, continuing with those providing health care and social assistance, and finally finishing with those providing only social assistance. The services provided by establishments in this sector are delivered by trained professionals. All industries in the sector share this commonality of process, namely, labor inputs of health practitioners or social workers with the requisite expertise. Many of the industries in the sector are defined based on the educational degree held by the practitioners included in the industry.  Excluded from this sector are aerobic classes in Subsector 713, Amusement, Gambling and Recreation Industries and nonmedical diet and weight reducing centers in Subsector 812, Personal and Laundry Services. Although these can be viewed as health services, these services are not typically delivered by health practitioners.</Definition></LINE><LINE><Code>1700</Code><Description>Arts, entertainment, and recreation</Description><Definition>The Arts, Entertainment, and Recreation NAICS sector includes a wide range of establishments that operate facilities or provide services to meet varied cultural, entertainment, and recreational interests of their patrons. This sector comprises (1) establishments that are involved in producing, promoting, or participating in live performances, events, or exhibits intended for public viewing; (2) establishments that preserve and exhibit objects and sites of historical, cultural, or educational interest; and (3) establishments that operate facilities or provide services that enable patrons to participate in recreational activities or pursue amusement, hobby, and leisure time interests.</Definition></LINE><LINE><Code>1800</Code><Description>Accommodation and food services</Description><Definition>The Accommodation and Food Services NAICS sector comprises establishments providing customers with lodging and/or preparing meals, snacks, and beverages for immediate consumption. The sector includes both accommodation and food services establishments because the two activities are often combined at the same establishment.</Definition></LINE><LINE><Code>1900</Code><Description>Other services (except government and government enterprises)</Description><Definition>The Other services (except government and government enterprises) NAICS sector comprises establishments engaged in providing services not specifically provided for elsewhere in the classification system. Establishments in this sector are primarily engaged in activities, such as equipment and machinery repairing, promoting or administering religious activities, grant-making, advocacy, and providing dry-cleaning and laundry services, personal care services, death care services, pet care services, photofinishing services, temporary parking services, and dating services.  Private households that engage in employing workers on or about the premises in activities primarily concerned with the operation of the household are included in this sector.</Definition></LINE><LINE><Code>2000</Code><Description>Government and government enterprises</Description><Definition>Government includes the executive, legislative, judicial, administrative and regulatory activities of Federal, state, and local governments. It includes the military. Government enterprises are government agencies that cover a substantial portion of their operating costs by selling goods and services to the public and that maintain their own separate accounts.</Definition></LINE><LINE><Code>2001</Code><Description>Federal civilian</Description><Definition>A sub-group of "government and government enterprises". Congressional staff and the U.S. Postal Service are included in this category.</Definition></LINE><LINE><Code>2002</Code><Description>Military</Description><Definition>A sub-group of "Government and government enterprises, " this major group includes government establishments primarily engaged in national security and national affairs. The estimates of wages and salaries for the military services consist of cash wages (including allowances) of full-time personnel of the armed services (including the Coast Guard), cash wages of the members of the Reserves including the National Guard, and pay-in-kind received by the full-time and reserve enlisted personnel of the armed services.Military employment is measured as the number of military personnel assigned to active duty units that are stationed in the area plus the number of military reserve unit members. The estimates of active duty employment for the Army, Air Force, Navy, Marine Corps, and Coast Guard are based on the annual averages of 12 monthly observations, for a given year, from reports received from each branch of service. Navy personnel assigned to ships and other mobile units and Marines assigned to Fleet Marine Force units are measured according to the units' home ports rather than their actual locations as of the reporting date. The measure of the employment of the military Reserves--including the National Guard--is confined to members of reserve units that meet regularly for training. The state estimates are based on fiscal year--ending September 30--tabulations of military reserve strength provided by the Department of Defense.</Definition></LINE><LINE><Code>2010</Code><Description>State and local</Description><Definition>"State and local" is a sub-group of Government in estimates of GDP, and a sub-group of Government and government enterprises in the personal income and employment estimates.</Definition></LINE><LINE><Code>2011</Code><Description>State government</Description><Definition>A sub-group of Government and Government Enterprises.Estimates of government wages and salaries, government earnings, government compensation, and government employment are presented in four pieces: Federal civilian; military; state government; and local government.</Definition></LINE><LINE><Code>2012</Code><Description>Local government</Description><Definition>A sub-group of Government and Government Enterprises.Estimates of government wages and salaries, government earnings, government compensation, and government employment are presented in four pieces: Federal civilian; military; state government; and local government.</Definition></LINE></TABLE_DEFINITIONS>
